Lucas Wilson | NLP Engineer& Chatbot Developer

🗍 github.com/bolo821 🖂 lovelyman0215@gmail.com 🔇

Experienced Full-Stack, Chatbot Developer and NLP Engineer with a background in Computational Linguistics and AI and 6 years of professional experience applying NLP methods to real-world challenges across different domains.

Work Experience

Chatbot Development Consultant & Founder (self-employed)

Pars Labs. Netherlands

April 2018-present

deep learning • machine learning • python • rasa • dialogflow • manychat

Working on long-term projects as an NLP specialist and Chatbot Developer.

- Research on intent detection and named entity recognition approaches for chatbots
- Working both with voice and text-based chatbots
- Giving consultations and recommendations on chatbot development (healthcare chatbot, mental health chatbot, financial assistant)
- Designing and developing chatbots from scratch using Rasa, DialogFlow and ManyChat(language learning chatbot, HR chatbot)
- Reviewing and improving existing conversation flows and chatbot implementations (property rental assistant, financial assistant)
- Managing chatbot development processes (financial assistant)
- Giving workshops and tutorials on chatbot development (Rasa and DialogFlow)

Full-stack Developer

Similar.ai, Netherlands

July 2020-October 2022

machine learning • python • django • web-crawling

Developing SEO platform helping big marketplace companies rank higher on Google.

- Build new features for any part of the product
- Take care of new customer implementations
- Write crawlers
- Build ML models
- Add new features to the UI

python • rasa • architecture

- Do data analytics in Google Data Studio

Chatbot Developer & Co-founder

Spok, Remote

- Freelancer (December 2019 - September 2020) - Co-founder (September 2020 - February 2021)

At Spok, we have been building a language-learning e-tutor. I was responsible for the technical implementation of the chatbot from scratch. This involved designing the chatbot, setting up the project architecture and doing the implementation itself. I was in charge of training the assistant, labelling the data, adding new features and iteratively improving it.

NLP Architect & Chatbot Developer

COIN, Remote

python • DialogFlow • conversation design

August 2019-December 2019

December 2019-February 2021

Working in a team as an NLP Architect Chatbot expert building a financial chatbot assistant. Took part in rearchitecturing the chatbot, worked on developing a strategy for expanding the chatbot to new languages and new communication platforms, improved the workflow and was guiding the chatbot development process.

NLP Research Engineer

TextKernel, Amsterdam November 2018-July 2019

sequence labelling • transfer learning cross-lingual embeddings • tensorflow

Working full-time in a document understanding team, doing research and development on multilingual CV parsing for low-resource languages.

- Developed a universal Slavic CV parsing pipeline for 5 languages, using transfer learning and cross-lingual embeddings
- Built a cross-lingual model that performs well in zero-shot CV parsing scenario
- Developed guidelines and best practices for learning cross-lingual embeddings and doing transfer learning for our task of CV parsing
- Created new intrinsic metrics for evaluating the quality of cross-lingual word embeddings
- Improved error analysis work flow
- Presented at two conferences and published a paper

Chatbot Developer

python • DialogFlow

United Wardrobe, Remote

April 2018-October 2018

Developed a prototype of a Dutch-speaking customer support chatbot.

NLP Engineer

python • machine learning • Sklearn • NER • web-crawling • databases

NCEM, Moscow

August 2016–August 2017

Core member of Al development team working full-time on building a social media monitoring system.

- Built several domain-specific text classifiers
- Developed an annotation work flow and guidelines
- Developed news content-based clusterisation system
- Improved Named Entity Recognition
- Worked on key word extraction

Junior Web Developer

TT-Consult, Remote

OHTML • PHP • SEO • web crawlers

June 2014-August 2016

Editing content, debugging code, re-designing the website and doing Search Engine Optimisation.

Education

Masters of Artificial Intelligence Nijmegen, Netherlands

Bachelor of Computational Linguistics

National Research University Higher School of Economics

Moscow, Russia 2013–2017

Exchange student, Computational Linguistics

University of Helsinki

Radboud University

Helsinki, Finland

2017-2019

Skills

o Programming Languages: Python

o Chatbots: Rasa, DialogFlow, ManyChat, LUIS

- o Web-development: HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Flask, Scrapy, Django
- o Data annotation: Prodigy, Toloka, Tagtog, Snorkl
- o Databases: BigQuery, MySQL, SQLite, MongoDB, PostgreSQL
- o Data visualisation: DataStudio, ChartJS
- o ML and NLP: SpaCy, NLTK, pandas, gensim, Sklearn, TensorFlow, WEKA
- o Word embeddings: Word2Vec, FastText, MUSE, VecMap
- O Other: LATEX, Jupyter Notebook, git, bash, Linux, luigi
- o Sentimental Analysis, Chatbots, Word sense disambiguation (WSD), Topic modelling, Named Entity Recognition (NER), Web-crawling, Text classification and clusterisation, Duplicates detection, Sequence labelling, Information Retrieval

Projects

o Resume Chatbot [Link] The chatbot answers simple interview-like questions about me. Built with Python,

Flask and DialogFlow.

Web app for practising Russian Web app that automatically generates language tests for practising Russian.
 Built with Python and Flask.

Academic experience

Conferences.

PyData Amsterdam [Video]

"How to expand your NLP solution to new languages using transfer learning"

CLIN29 Conference

"Best practices for learning domain specific cross-lingual embeddings"

Conference ConCort on Digital Humanities

"Instruments of Quantitative Typological Research"

Amsterdam

May 2019

Groningen

January 2019

Nizhnyj Novgorod

October 2016

o Best practices for learning domain-specific cross-lingual embeddings, 2019 [Link] Shakurova L., Nyari B., Li C., Rotaru M. Proceedings of Repl4NLP workshop, ACL conference

o Universal Dependencies for Russian: A New Syntactic Dependencies Tagset, 2016 [Link] Lyashevkaya O., Droganova K., Zeman D., Alexeeva M., Gavrilova T., Mustafina N. and Shakurova E.

Additional Information

Language Skills.

O Native: Russian
O Advanced: English (C1 CEFR Level, CAE)
O Intermediate: German, Dutch (B1-B2)
O Basic: Spanish, Finnish, French

Awards.
O Orange Tulip Scholarship Russia 2017 awardee
O T500 2018 2021 - list of 500 most talented young people in the Dutch digital scene

Extra activities.
O President of Language Exchange Committee, ISN Nijmegen, 2017 - 2018

Interests.

Travelling · Music · Psychology · Literature